<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>HrachBlog - Rants</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/rants.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2016-09-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>GeForce Experience</title><link href="/geforce-experience.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-09-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Frank Hrach</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-09-27:/geforce-experience.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The NVidia vs. AMD competition is less of a debate, and more of a fact of life at this point. AMD will continue to
play second fiddle and make better value graphics cards, but if you value performance over all else you will always
buy NVidia. This unchanging market has …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The NVidia vs. AMD competition is less of a debate, and more of a fact of life at this point. AMD will continue to
play second fiddle and make better value graphics cards, but if you value performance over all else you will always
buy NVidia. This unchanging market has started to become anti-consumer in recent years. NVidia has slowly begun to
abuse its market dominance to both raise the price of cards, and push more and more unnecessary products on its
users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest in this series of business decisions is the update to GeForce Experience. For those who are unaware,
GeForce Experience is a program which downloads optimal settings for games based off of your system specs and
includes a number of utilities provided by NVidia such as shadowplay. No one ever uses either of these two
features, and instead, GeForce experience is nothing more than a glorified auto-updater for graphics drivers. Gone
were the days of going to a website, downloading an installer, and running it every time there was a minor update
to the graphics driver. For a brief, glorious, period, GeForce Experience did all of the above features with the
added bonus of downloading and installing updated drivers when they became available. And then version 3.0 came
out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting in version 3.0, usage of GeForce Experience requires the user to create an account, the reasoning being
that NVidia can sync settings between your computers. This is a load of grade A bullshit. I don't want my setting
synced across my computers, I only have one computer with an NVidia graphics card, and if I had a laptop with one,
I'd want to have a different set of in-game settings because it would be a less powerful machine. The &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; thing
I want GeForce Experience to do is to connect to NVidia's website and download drivers. This now &lt;strong&gt;requires&lt;/strong&gt; I be
logged in to NVidia's bullshit service. We all know the reason they are doing this is to generate user profiles for
advertisers. Once they can associate your playing and purchase habits with a username, they can use that
information for market research and to sell advertising space. It is a disturbingly common practice in this day and
age, and the worst part is I'll still use it. NVidia makes their installers such a pain to download and use and
they &lt;strong&gt;know&lt;/strong&gt; most people will be like me and simply deal with it because the convenience of using their service
beats out their archaic and needlessly painful old install process. The only reason they can get away with this
shit is because AMD hasn't managed to put out a truly competitive card in years.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="30 Day Challenge"></category></entry><entry><title>YouTube Heroes</title><link href="/youtube-heroes.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-24T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-09-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Frank Hrach</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-09-24:/youtube-heroes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'll admit this is low-hanging fruit, but, this needs to be said: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Wh_1966vaIA"&gt;YouTube Heroes&lt;/a&gt; is proof that YouTube both doesn't
understand and can act without fear of failure due to it's position in the market. I may not be a content creator,
but I spend a lot of time on …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'll admit this is low-hanging fruit, but, this needs to be said: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Wh_1966vaIA"&gt;YouTube Heroes&lt;/a&gt; is proof that YouTube both doesn't
understand and can act without fear of failure due to it's position in the market. I may not be a content creator,
but I spend a lot of time on YouTube, sometimes, I even dive into the comments section sometimes. I can say that,
without a doubt, YouTube Heroes will be a negative force for the website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;YouTube Is Out of Touch With its Users&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anything, the release of YouTube Heroes confirms that the YouTube staff has no idea what the users of it's
website want or need. I constantly hear content creators complain that they don't have the moderation tools they
need to properly manage their comment sections, to the point that may simply disable them and direct their viewers
to Reddit or Twitter to discuss the video. Specifically, a common complaint I hear is moderators are unable to hide
a user's comment, they can only ban users. Bans don't work on trolls, since they will just create a new account and
say something even more vile and inflammatory, fueled by the knowledge that they are getting a reaction from both
the owner of the channel and the rest of the comment section. A much more useful tool, is to simply hide the
comment or account so that no one can see it. It takes much more time for a troll to figure out that no one can see
what they wrote, always leaving the possibility that no one is taking their bait. The kicker here is, only the
channel admin has the ability to do this, not any of the moderates they appoint. A simple fix for the comments
section, assuming that the goal of YouTube Heroes is to clean up the site, would be to simply give moderators that
ability as well. Instead, YouTube thought that a good solution was to let members of the community who prove
themselves through a perverse set of incentives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here lies the biggest problem with the YouTube Heroes program. Members earn points to "level up" and receive
new abilities and benefits. A few of the tasks are relatively harmless, such as answering a question on a help
forum or submitting some subtitles for a video that get accepted, however, most rely on moderating user-generated
content. Additionally, the system rewards flagging videos, comments, and other moderation features far more than
the other and more helpful contributions. Even more concerning, is at level 3, users are granted the ability to
bulk-flag videos. I cannot imagine how this passed any meeting, since community moderation like that &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; works
as soon as personal politics get involved, just take a look at any mildly controversial Wikipedia article's
discussion page. All that will result in is a ton of flags because a user doesn't like the content of a video
instead of for legitimate reasons for breaking rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;YouTube is a Monopoly&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If these features were launched on just about any other website, there would be a mass exodus of users to an
alternative platform- the &lt;a href="http://reddithistory.wikia.com/wiki/Digg_exodus"&gt;Great Digg Migration / Reddit Exodus&lt;/a&gt;
comes to mind. However, there is no suitable place on the internet to replace YouTube. A video site lives and dies
by it's viewers and content creators. There needs to be a large enough viewer base to attract content creators,
and, content creators need to make new content to keep users. This creates a chicken-and-egg problem where a new
platform has both no users and no content creators so there is no reason for users to switch. Furthermore, even if
there is a reason to switch, the startup costs and risks of a video streaming website are so high that there are
nearly zero new video websites, at least, video websites that let anyone upload whatever they want to get started.
Since they have, essentially, zero risk of failure, YouTube has made a long series of awful decisions which the
users hate, but, they have nowhere else to go. YouTube is where both the viewers and content creators are, and
sadly, I don't see that changing anytime soon.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="30 Day Challenge"></category><category term="YouTube"></category></entry><entry><title>The Plight of the Healer</title><link href="/the-plight-of-the-healer.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-16T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-09-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Frank Hrach</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-09-16:/the-plight-of-the-healer.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The healer class... also known as the team gimp of the online gaming world. When a team wins in a MOBA, or more recently, in Overwatch, the offense classes generally get the glory - the flankers, the tanks, the AD-Carry, the Nukers. However, when the team loses, blame quickly shifts to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The healer class... also known as the team gimp of the online gaming world. When a team wins in a MOBA, or more recently, in Overwatch, the offense classes generally get the glory - the flankers, the tanks, the AD-Carry, the Nukers. However, when the team loses, blame quickly shifts to the healer. "Why didn't you heal me?", "Where were you the entire match?", and  "Way to go healer". As someone who tends to play support this is infuriating because it's no one's fault when a team loses. A team can fail for any number of reasons, but usually it's because the offense and support don't work together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A healer is no good if there is no one around to heal, and likewise, an attacker isn't going to be very effective if they need to seek out health pickups constantly. A good team works together, the offense not straying too far from the healer so they can actually keep them alive, and, the offense can also protect the vulnerable healer from the enemy team- after all, dead supports don't heal. I bring this up because 99% of the time I get yelled at for being a bad healer, it's by an asshole who is so far out of position behind the enemy lines that it's impossible to even get to them. And, if I can get just one more good game because of someone reading this post, I'll be happy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gaming"></category><category term="30 Day Challenge"></category></entry><entry><title>The Failed Promises of Linux Gaming</title><link href="/the-failed-promises-of-linux-gaming.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-03-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2015-03-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Frank Hrach</name></author><id>tag:None,2015-03-09:/the-failed-promises-of-linux-gaming.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Way back in 2013, Valve software announced their intention to bring PC gaming to Linux and the world rejoiced. Finally we could be free of the shackles of Microsoft and paid operating systems! We could ascend into a new era of better performance due to the lower overhead of OpenGL …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Way back in 2013, Valve software announced their intention to bring PC gaming to Linux and the world rejoiced. Finally we could be free of the shackles of Microsoft and paid operating systems! We could ascend into a new era of better performance due to the lower overhead of OpenGL, and enjoy more customization. For those unwilling to take the plunge into Linux, Valve announced Steam OS: a Linux based operating system designed for gaming first. Steam OS would be loaded on Steam Machines designed to take PC gaming to the living room and free console users from the tyranny of Sony, Microsoft, and Nintendo. We would all be moved into a gaming utopia under the light of Gaben. Half Life 3 would finally be confirmed! All gaming Internet arguments would end, and we would all sing Kumbaya around a virtual campfire rendered in the Source 2 engine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to 2015. Steam OS is finally coming out of beta, but no one other than the hardcore audience seems to care or even remember they exist. Steam machines are finally becoming a reality, though not until November of 2015. The current console generation will have been out for three years already and had had time to establish itself. The Steam Machines that have been announced are certainly not console-killers. Even worse, they don't make the transition to PC gaming any easier. There are multiple models of Steam Machines with drastically different pricepoints and performance. The cheaper models will not compete with the current generation of consoles for raw power. The higher end boxes are more expensive than a console, and are more expensive then building an equivalent machine from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steam OS has been stuck in perpetual beta for years. While it is too early to pass judgment upon it, it has caused a significant number of games to be ported to Linux. This has been a positive for the industry and the consumer, but consumers are not getting exactly what was advertised. Valve showcased a Linux build of Left 4 Dead 2 playing at a higher framerate than the Windows version claiming that switching to Linux will yield better performance due to decreased driver overhead. Valve also announced a toolkit to make porting games from Windows easier. This turned out to be a double edged sword. While many games are currently available for Linux that probably would not otherwise been ported, many are poor quality ports that are inferior at best and completely incompatible at worst when compared to their Windows counterparts. Furthermore, even with this toolkit a truly disappointing number of ports are  just a wine wrapper, which mostly works but is not an improvement over what was done before. For the most part, only Valve games offer an equivalent or superior experience on Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll use a few examples of high-profile games I have had major issues with. These range from minor usability complaints, to missing features, to things which completely and totally break the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was excited for Borderlands 2 and Civilization V to come to Linux. I also feared that my productivity would go down the toilet with two of my most addicting games on my Linux install. I didn't have to worry though. The save files are not compatible between Windows and Linux for Borderlands 2 and for Civilization V. The files don't sync properly from the Linux versions, so any progress on my Linux install would not transfer to my Windows install. This is not a deal breaker for Civilization, but completely unacceptable for Borderlands 2. I can't use my character across installs like I could with a second Windows machine. This might be acceptable five years ago, before cloud saves became common, but is currently unacceptable. As for Civilization V, one of its most interesting features is the Steam Workshop integration, which allows for incredibly easy modding. This is simply absent in the Linux version, rather, it is disabled by default and the only way to enable it is through config editing. I understand that the feature is technically in beta, but Workshop support is advertised on the game's store page! Even when you enable the option in the menu it still warns the user with a pop-up. There is no reason for the Steam Workshop to be disabled by default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Borderlands and Civilization suffer from the same problem: they are ported by a third party, Aspyr. Aspyr does an admirable job porting games to Linux, but, they seem to always be incompatible with the windows version managed by the development team. This represents the worst cop-out of Linux gaming, in my opinion. Borderlands and Civilization are often cites as evidence of big-budget AAA games having  a presence on Linux, however, both games come with a HUGE asterisk: your data is incompatible if you also have a Windows install of the game. So while they are present, they almost live in their own little world. This will be a huge issue for someone who wanted to play their Borderlands character on a Steam Machine that they started on their existing gaming PC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dota 2 is next on the chopping block. It holds the distinguished honor of being the only MOBA game available on Linux, so you'd think this would be listed as a positive. However, as most gamers, I run a muti-monitor setup. On Linux, this means setting up Twinview, which breaks an astounding number of Games. Dota 2 is not broken by Twinview, but it is incapable of locking the cursor to the game Window on Linux. If you have played a MOBA, it is obvious how this makes the game literally unplayable. Every time I try and scroll, the game loses focus. Every time I get a bit excited, and over-react with the mouse, it leaves the screen and I click, bringing the game out of focus. This results in near instant death because every fraction of a second matters in a MOBA, even at the low level of play I am capable of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the most positive game on my list is Wargame: Red Dragon. Wargame is unique because it actually does not use Valve's cloud or authentication service, and actually functions properly on Linux because of it. My profile is stored on Eugen's servers, and I never have to worry about losing my data between sessions. The major issue with Wargame is it's performance. The game crashes on Linux far more than it does on Windows, and, it has rendering issues with shadows. The final nail in the coffin is the framerate. Red Dragon is a demanding game, but I should never be getting sub 30fps on a GTX 980 with it. The game runs above 60 at all times on Windows, and rarely above 60 on Linux. Almost every game performs worse on Linux than on Windows, but Wargame is one of the worst performing Linux games I own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the whole, the rest of the industry does not seem to be as gung-ho about Linux gaming as Valve was back in 2013. Gaming on Linux is still an incomplete experience where the user makes many compromises for choosing Linux over Windows. The only benefits are ideological. Maybe Steam OS will change things, but for the time being, the industry treats Linux gamers as second-class citizens, and until more people adopt Linux or Steam OS, they will always be treated as such.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Rants"></category><category term="Gaming"></category></entry><entry><title>YouTube's UI is Shit... Part 1</title><link href="/youtubes-ui-is-shit-part-1.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-01-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2015-01-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Frank Hrach</name></author><id>tag:None,2015-01-27:/youtubes-ui-is-shit-part-1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'll start this post by stating that I am in no way an expert in user interface design, I spend enough time on YouTube as a user to notice some glaring flaws. The fact that I am &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; an expert and yet still feel qualified should highlight on how bad …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'll start this post by stating that I am in no way an expert in user interface design, I spend enough time on YouTube as a user to notice some glaring flaws. The fact that I am &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; an expert and yet still feel qualified should highlight on how bad YouTube's UI really is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What's Wrong?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll start with seemingly the most basic part of the UI: viewing a user's uploads. You should try this with me now. Go open an uploader's uploads page. At the bottom middle of the screen there is a button which says "Load More". Click this button and watch any video on the part of the page that loads. When you have finished enjoying your video of choice, hit back. Oh look! You are at the top of the uploads page again. This problem is even worse when an uploader has hundreds and hundreds of videos. As a user, you must rely on an uploader organizing all of their videos into playlists, or rely on searching by video name (provided you know part of the name of the video you want to find). I have no idea how this has continued to pass even the most basic of user experience tests for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How to Fix it&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few options here. First, make each video open on a different tab or different window. This is a simple fix, but I personally think that any design that requires the user to manage multiple tabs is an example of poor design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another easy option is to move back to a standard page system. This is not as "sexy" of a design option as the single page model, but the user can actually pick up where they left off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final option could be to find a way to remember where the user left off on the endless scrolling page. I'm not entirely sure how this is implemented, but other sites utilize it. Go to Facebook, and open a link partway down the page then return. When you navigate back it remembers your position and returns roughly to where you left off.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Rants"></category><category term="UI"></category><category term="Youtube"></category></entry></feed>